Guide to the Radio Haiti Papers, circa 1934-2003, bulk 1968-2003 RL.11499
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Impunity and Dictatorship, 1957-2003
  - Assassinations and Murders, 1982-2003
    - Mireille Durocher Bertin assassination, 1995-1996; 1 folder (Box 112)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the 1995 assassination of right-wing lawyer and Aristide opponent, Mireille Durocher Bertin. Dany Toussaint denies beind involves in the assassination. External material includes news (much of it translated from English to French).
    - Jean-Hubert Feuillé assassination, 1995-1998; 1 folder (Box 112)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the 1995 assassination of Lavalas parliamentarian Jean-Hubert Feuillé and attempted assassination of parliamentarian Gabriel Fortuné. External materials include news, press releases by civil society and government ministries.
    - Jean-Marie Vincent assassination, 1995-2002; 1 folder (Box 112)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the August 1994 assassination of liberation theology priest Jean-Marie Vincent. Includes commemorations and the search for justice, press releases, and materials from the Fondation Jean-Marie Vincent.
    - Antoine Izméry assassination, 1995-2002; 1 folder (Box 112)
      See also: Coup d'état; National calendar
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the September 11, 1993 assassination of businessman and human rights activist Antoine Izméry, including US Immigration's 2001 arrest of former FAd'H captain Jackson Joannis in connection with Izméry's murder. External materials include minutes from the criminal court, and OEA/ONU's report on Izméry assassination.
    - Guy Malary assassination, 1995-2003; 1 folder (Box 112)
      See also: Coup d'état
      Radio Haiti and external materials relating to the 1993 assassination of Minister of Justice Guy Malary.
    - Various killings, 1995-2003; 1 folder (Box 112)
      See also: Ensekirite
      Small quantities of Radio Haiti materials and external relating to various killings, including local politicians, former military, civilians, UN. External materials include news.
    - Assassination of Emilio Passe, 1997; 1 folder (Box 112)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the October 1997 assassination of Louis Emilio Passe, parliament member from Dame-Marie. External materials include news, statements and tributes from KID, KOREGA, among others.
    - Assassination of Father Jean "Ti Jan" Pierre-Louis, 1998-2001; 2 folders (Box 112)
      See also: Organisations populaires
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on the August 3, 1998 assassination of liberation theology priest Jean "Ti Jan" Pierre-Louis, including reactions, commemorations, and investigation. External materials include news, commemorations, press releases, declarations by grassroots groups.
    - Assassinations of Yvon Toussaint and Jimmy Lalanne, 1999-2000; 2 folders (Box 113)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials on the assassination of OPL senator Yvon Toussaint on March 1, 1999 and the murder of Dr. Jimmy Lalanne on February 27, 1999. Because these events occurred in such proximity, they are often reported on together. External materials include news, declarations and press releases from government and civil society groups, including MPP, Fondation Aristide (Myrlande Libérus), and others.
    - P. Espérance, E. Leblanc; P. Merisier assassination attempts, 1999-2002; 1 folder (Box 113)
      Radio Haiti materials on the 1999 attempt on the life of NCHR director Pierre Esperance, 2001 attempt on the life of former senator Edgard Leblanc, and the 2002 attempt on the life of NCHR staff member Patrick Merisier.
    - Assassination of Deputé Tenor, 2000; 1 folder (Box 113)
      Radio Haiti materials on the assassination of member of parliament Rood Tenor Guerrier.
    - Murder of Jeannot Succès, 2000; 1 folder (Box 113)
      See also: Haiti-Dominican Republic
      Radio Haiti materials on the 2000 death of a young Haitian migrant Jeannot Succès at the hands of the Dominican military.
    - Murder of Amos Jeannot, 2000-2002; 1 folder (Box 113)
      Radio Haiti materials on the 2000 kidnapping and murder of young FONKOZE employee Amos Jeannot.
    - Assassination of Marc-André Dirogène, 2001-2002; 2 folders (Box 113)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the February 2002 assassination of Lavalas parliamentarian from Gonaïves, Marc-André Dirogène. External materials include news, fliers from the funeral, and Dirogène's letters denouncing corruption in the APN in 2001.
    - Murder of three young brothers, Waney 89, Carrefour, 2002-2003; 1 folder (Box 113)
      See also: Police
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the December 2002 killing of three young brothers by the National Police in Waney 89, Carrefour. External materials include news and a declaration by the victims' parents.
    - Murder of Eric Pierre, 2003; 1 folder (Box 113)
      Radio Haiti materials relating to the killing of medical student Eric Pierre.
    - Murder of Peter Oléus, 2003; 1 folder (Box 113)
      Radio Haiti materials relating to the killing of 17-year-old Peter Oleus.
  - Attempted assassination of Michèle Montas/Death of Maxime Seïde, 2002-2003
    - Amnesty International Letter Campaign, 2003; 5 folders (Box 113)
      Letters written by Amnesty International members from various countries, to President Jean Bertrand Aristide, Prime Minister Yvon Neptune, and Minister of Justice Calixte Delatour to express concern for the safety of Michèle Montas and the Radio Haiti journalists, and to demand justice for Jean Dominique, Jean-Claude Louissaint, and Maxime Seïde. Copies were sent to Radio Haiti, often including additional notes of support. Mainly in English, French, German, Spanish.
    - Radio Haiti texts, 2002-2003; 2 folders (Box 114)
      Radio Haiti's written materials (on-air scripts) and external materials relating to the December 25, 2002 attempted assassination of Michèle Montas in which her bodyguard, Maxime Seïde, was killed. External materials include news, letter from Father Jan Hanssens, and declarations from NCHR and Fondasyon Eko Vwa Jean Dominique.
  - Corruption and Corporate Crime, 1983-2003 (bulk 1987-2003)
    - Corruption, 1983; 1987-1991; 1 folder (Box 114)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about corruption and embezzlement, including Stanley Théard of SOPRINA's contract with Minister of Finance Frantz Merceron (1983) and the Mourra banking fraud case.
    - Corruption, 1995-1998; 2 folders (Box 114)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about corruption and embezzlement, including state corruption, false checks (chèques zonbis), Opération Mains Propres, and corruption within Téléco and the DGI.
    - Corruption, 1999-2003; 1 folder (Box 114)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about corruption and embezzlement, including state corruption, corruption within the Autorité Portuaire Nationale and the Darbonne sugar factory, and other cases.
    - Gérard Dumont, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box 114)
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials relating to the Gérard Dumont banking fraud case. Money-lender Gérard Dumont fled Haiti in 1986 with a reported $20 million that had been put into escrow, mainly by small-scale merchants. External materials include letters from lawyer Lafontant Joseph, who was defending the defrauded merchants.
    - Pharval (1-2 of 9), 1995-2002; 2 folders (Box 114)
      See also: Health
      Radio Haiti materials (on-air scripts and Jean Dominique's notes) and external materials concerning the Pharval scandal, in which children went into kidney failure after consuming cough syrup containing diethylene glycol. External materials include a report by Ludo Martens of the Organisation Panamericaine de la Santé/Organisation Mondiale de la Santé (OPS/OMS, PAHO/WHO) evaluating pharmaceutical company Pharval (September 1995); Ministère de la Santé Publique et de la Population (MSPP) documents relating to Pharval, diethylene glycol poisoning, acute renal failure in children, and pharmaceuticals in Haiti in general (1996-1997); US Food and Drug Administration preliminary report on Pharval, diethylene glycol and the acute renal failure epidemic in Haiti; the Centers for Disease Control's Preliminary Report on Pharval, diethylene glycol and the acute renal failure epidemic; communication from OPS/OMS to Prime Minister Rosny Smarth; "Transparence" newsletter from Pharval; communication from Pharval; press release from the Association des Parents des Enfants Rescapés de l'Intoxication au D.E.G. en Haïti; letter from MSPP to Rudolph Boulos; open letter from the Comité des Parents Victimes des Medicaments Pharval.
    - Pharval (3-9 of 9), 1995-2002; 7 folders (Box 115)
    - TEVASA (1-3 of 5), 1996-1997; 3 folders (Box 115)
      Radio Haiti scripts and external materials relating to the TEVASA affair. Includes full minutes of the Haitian Senate's hearing on the contract between TEVASA (Terminal Varreux S.A.), owned by the Mevs family, and the Haitian state; the Senate's report on the hearing on the contract between TEVASA and the state; TEVASA-produced documents concerning the petroleum contract between the TEVASA port and the Haitian government. Radio Haiti scripts relate to the investigation into the TEVASA port's petroleum contract with the Haitian government.
    - TEVASA (4-5 of 5), 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 116)
  - Coup d'État, 1991-2001
    - "Les sept mois de la présidence du père Jean-Bertrand Aristide", November 1991; 1 folder (Box 116)
      "Les sept mois de la présidence du père Jean-Bertrand Aristide: Mémoire pour l'histoire et pour les amis du peuple haïtien." Author not identified. Annex includes press clippings, letters, petitions.
    - "Pour convertir nos revers en victoire", December 1991; 1 folder (Box 116)
      Document by the Comité d'Initiative de l'Organisation Lavalas following the overthrow of Aristide.
    - Alerte Belance, 1994; 1 folder (Box 116)
      Materials about the torture and attempted murder of Alerte Belance, an Aristide supporter who was kidnapped, hacked with a machete, and left for dead in October 1993. Includes Belance's civil lawsuit against FRAPH in a New York court, where she was represented by the Center for Constitutional Rights.
    - Amnesty International, 1992-1994; 1 folder (Box 116)
      Amnesty International reports and press releases about the coup years in Haiti. Includes "Haiti: Human Rights Held to Ransom"(August 1992), "Haiti: On the Horns of a Dilemma: Military Repression or Foreign Invasion?" and its French version, "Haïti: Répression Militaire ou Invasion Étrangère: un Terrible Dilemme" (August 1994).
    - Antoine Izméry, 1992-1994; 1 folder (Box 116)
      See also: Antoine Izméry assassination
      Antoine Izméry's strongly-worded fax to US President George Bush after Bush lost the 1992 election. Press release from Komite Mete Men Pou Verite Blayi (6 September 1993) in which Izméry, Père Yvon Massac, and Fabono Saint-Vil announce the commemoration of the Saint-Jean Bosco massacre, at which Izméry would be killed five days later. MICIVIH's report on Izméry's assassination.
    - Aristide government in exile, 1992-1994; 2 folders (Box 116)
      See also: Governors Island accord
      Materials by and about Jean-Bertrand Aristide's government in exile. Include's Aristide's cabinet, meetings and communications with UN and OAS, negotiations, Ambassador Jean Casimir, Aristide's 18 November 1993 message to the Haitian people, the January 1994 "Démocratie: La Solution à la Crise Haïtienne" conference in Miami, and other materials.
    - Bassin Caïman massacre, M. Montas notes, 1994; 1 folder (Box 116)
      Handwritten notes by Michèle Montas on the Bassin Caïman/Borgne massacre in April 1994. Notes undated.
    - Coalition for Civilian Observers in Haiti (report), 1993; 1 folder (Box 116)
      The Coalition for Civilian Observers in Haiti's report "Internal Exile in Haiti: A Country Held Hostage by Its Own Army." (Research conducted September-November 1992, report published January 1993.)
    - Council on Hemispheric Affairs, 1992-1993; 1 folder (Box 116)
      Press releases from the Council on Hemispheric Affairs. Also includes handwritten note from Larry Birns to Jean Dominique and Michèle Montas, with a collection of other press.
    - FAd'H communication, 1993; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Communications from Michel François and Philippe Biamby (copies of Thermofax; difficult to read).
    - Fax to Jean-Bertrand Aristide, circa 1994; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Fax to Jean-Bertrand Aristide, cautioning him about becoming too close to the United States and Bill Clinton. Author not identified. Difficult to read.
    - Fondation 30 Septembre: "Agenda Noir", 1998; 1 folder (Box 117)
      See also: Human Rights
      Fondation 30 Septembre's draft for a calendar of a chronology of the events of the 1991-1994 coup years. The cover was designed to feature photographs of Alerte Belance, Father Jean-Marie Vincent, Antoine Izméry, and Guy Malary.
    - Foreign Broadcast Information Service, 1991; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Daily reports from the Foreign Broadcast Information Service, from September, October, and November 1991.
    - FRAPH, New York office, 1994; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Documents from and about FRAPH's New York branch, under Lyonel Sterling, Rigaud Noël, and Sylvestre Jean-Léger. Includes strongly-worded open letter to Boutros Boutros-Ghali about the UN's presence in Haiti, open letter to Emile Jonassaint calling Jean-Bertrand Aristide a traitor and a psychopath, and other documents. Also contains information about FRAPH-New York, including Sterling's home address. Materials seem to come from Haïti Observateur.
    - Governors Island accord, June-July 1993; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Materials relating to the June 27-July 3, 1993 conference at Governors Island, NY. Includes Jean Dominique's handwritten notes on the conference, Jean Dominique's typewritten analysis of the conference and media coverage of it, fliers and maps of Governors Island, the text of the Governors Island accord (in French and in English), a list of the members of the delegations (the Haitian government in exile, and the FAd'H), and UN documents.
    - Governors Island accord - press, 1993; 2 folders (Box 117)
      Press (mainly US sources) about the Governors Island meeting and accord.
    - Haiti Government/Business Partnership Conference, 1993; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Materials from the Haiti Government/Business Partnership Conference held in Miami from 22-23 July 1993, featuring participants from the US government, the US private sector, Haitian business institutions and organizations (including CLED, INDEPCO, ADIH, ANIPP, and many others), wealthy and influential people from the Haitian private sector (Nahoum Acra, Eric Behrmann, Gilbert Bigio, Réginald Boulos, Clifford Brandt, Carl Braun, Fritz Mevs, and many others), and finally the Haitian delegation (including Jean Dominique, Father Antoine Adrien, Mildred Trouillot, François Séverin, Marie Michèle Rey, Robert Malval, and many others).
    - Haiti Info, 1993-1994; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Four volumes of "Haiti Info" newsletter on the Governors Island accord, and the US occupation.
    - Haiti Reborn, 1992; 1 folder (Box 117)
      "Haiti Reborn" newsletter edited by Aristide supporter Steve Brescia.
    - Human Rights Watch/NCHR, 1993-1994; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Reports by Human Rights Watch/Americas and the National Coalition for Haitian Rights (NCHR) about human rights violations during the coup years in Haiti. "Silencing a People: The Destruction of Civil Society in Haiti" (1993) and "Terror Prevails in Haiti: Human Rights Violations and Failed Diplomacy" (1994).
    - Initial reactions and declarations, September-October 1991; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Initial reactions and declarations after the 30 September 1991 coup d'état that overthrew President Jean-Bertrand Aristide. Includes General Raoul Cédras's declaration, Jean-Bertrand Aristide's message and the declaration of the Comité d'Initiative de l'Organisation Lavalas, religious groups, Chavannes Jean-Baptiste of MPP, university students, the Haitian consulate, the United States, Captain Dany Toussaint (who resigns from the army), the Association des Industries d'Haïti, and others.
    - Jean L. Dominique's notes, May 1994; 1 folder (Box 117)
      Jean Dominique's date-by-date handwritten notes on news reporting about Haiti in May 1994.
    - Jean L. Dominique's notes: invasion, September 1994; 1 folder (Box 117)
      See also: Operation Uphold Democracy
      Jean Dominique's handwritten notes on news coverage of the US invasion of Haiti to restore Aristide, from 15-28 September 1994.
    - Justice and reparations, 1995-2001; 4 folders (Box 118)
      See also: Fondation 30 Septembre; Raboteau massacre
      Radio Haiti materials and external materials about commemorations of the coup years, and calls for justice and reparations for victims. Includes the CIA's seizure of FRAPH documents, possible extradition of members of the army and FRAPH, and other topics.
    - Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, 1991-1994; 1 folder (Box 118)
      Reports and statements by the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights about the human rights situation in Haiti during the coup years, as well as correspondence from Deputy Director William (Bill) O'Neil.
    - Miscellaneous, 1991-1994; 2 folder (Box 118)
      Various correspondence (mostly photocopies): Déjean Bélizaire's letter of denunciation to OAS; Jim Naureckas to the New York Times on biased reporting; correspondence between Aristide and UN Special Envoy Dante Caputo; fax from Gary Victor Promotional materials about the film "Krik? Krak! Tales of a Nightmare." Daily security reports. Publications or press releases from the Heritage Foundation, the Center for International Policy, the Center for Constitutional Rights, Haïti: Résistance et Démocratie information bulletins, Radio Soleil, FNCD, the Canadian mission to the OAS, the NAACP and TransAfrica, the Press Association of Jamaica. Also includes a draft project for "Louvri Barye A" and the Batistè Òganizasyon Politik Lavalas from August 1992.
    - National Labor Committee, 1993-1994; 1 folder (Box 119)
      Press releases and reports by the National Labor Committee Education Fund in Support of Worker and Human Rights in Central America. Includes report "Haiti After the Coup: Sweatshop or Real Development?"
    - OAS/CIDH, 1992-1994; 1 folder (Box 119)
      Press releases from the Inter-American Commission on Human Rights (ICHR/CIRH) of the Organization of American States about missions to Haiti to investigate the human rights situation.
    - Operation Uphold Democracy - press, September 1994; 2 folders (Box 119)
      Collection of press dispatches from 15-30 September 1994, on the military invasion Operation Uphold Democracy that restored Jean-Bertrand Aristide to power.
    - Press clippings (1-6 of 31), 1991-1994; 6 folders (Box 119)
      Press clippings collected by Jean Dominique during his exile in New York during the 1991-1994 coup years. Contains primarily US newspapers (New York Times, Washington Post, and others) but also contains French, Dominican, Haitian, and Haitian diaspora news sources. Subjects include the 30 September 1991 coup d'état and its immediate aftermath, Haitian refugees fleeing by sea (so-called "boat people") and their treatment at Guantánamo camp, US immigration policy toward Haitian refugees, the CIA's involvement paying members of the military junta and the CIA's report on Aristide's purported mental illness, protests and demonstrations by members of the Haitian diaspora, continued violence and deprivation in Haiti, attempts to arrange Aristide's return, the Governors Island accord (June-July 1993) US sanctions and the UN trade embargo against Haiti (October 1993) and the embargo's effects on the population, the assassinations of Antoine Izméry and Guy Malary, support for Aristide from abroad (including Randall Robinson's Transafrica and Hollywood celebrities), the presidency of Émil Jonassaint, the Bassin Caïman/Le Borgne massacre, Operation Uphold Demoracy and Aristide's return to Haiti (September-October 1994) and the beginnings of the occupation. Folders are arranged by month.
    - Press clippings (7-13 of 31), 1991-1994; 7 folders (Box 120)
    - Press clippings (14-21 of 31), 1991-1994; 8 folders (Box 121)
    - Press clippings (22-28 of 31), 1991-1994; 7 folders (Box 122)
    - Press clippings (29-31 of 31), 1991-1994; 3 folders (Box 123)
    - Press clippings: El Salvador, 1993-1994; 1 folder (Box 123)
      Press clippings collected by Jean Dominique during his exile in New York during the 1991-1994 coup years about US military aid to El Salvador during the Salvadoran Civil War.
    - Press clippings: Post-coup reconstruction, 1995-1996; 1 folder (Box 123)
      External press about reconstruction and reforms following the coup years and the return of Aristide's democratically-elected government. Includes CIA involvement, the CIA's seizure of FRAPH documents, privatization, and other topics. Also includes Allan Nairn's article in The Nation and Jean Dominique's typewritten translation of Nairn's article, and a transcript of a "60 Minutes" interview with Emmanuel "Toto" Constant.
    - Radio Haiti reports, September-October 1991; 1 folder (Box 123)
      Radio Haiti's reports from all over Haiti following the 30 September 1991 coup d'état.
    - Radyo Nèg Mawon, 1992; 1 folder (Box 123)
      External materials from and about Radyo Nèg Mawon and director Jean Jean-Pierre, Radio for Peace International, and Rocklanders for Democracy in Haiti (founded by Jonathan Demme).
    - Semaine "Haïti-Démocratie", 1994; 1 folder (Box 123)
      Program of the Semaine "Haïti-Démocratie" conference in Miami, from 28 March to 2 April 1994. Includes Jean Dominique's notes and invitations to Jean Dominique and Michèle Montas from Aristide.
    - United Nations (1-6 of 11), 1991-1994; 6 folders (Box 124)
      Documents produced by the United Nations, including news summaries, reports and communiqués from the General Assembly and Security Council, press releases. Also includes communication from Serge Gilles of PANPRA to special representative Dante Caputo, from Raoul Cédras to Boutros Boutros-Ghali, and other materials addressed to the UN. Includes the human rights situation in Haiti, sanctions imposed on Haiti, negotiations by special representative Dante Caputo, the Governors Island accord, peace-keeping operations and the creation of the joint UN-OAS mission MICIVIH, and other topics. Folders arranged by year.
    - United Nations (7-11 of 11), 1991-1994; 5 folders (Box 125)
    - US involvement, 1992-1995; 1 folder (Box 125)
      Various materials about US involvement in Haiti. Includes communication between Paul Cassagnol of UPH and Senator Alphonse Amato (1991); Gérard Jean-Juste's press release on Bush's loss in the 1992 election; communication from the Congressional Black Caucus to Bill Clinton; the US Department of State's response to Marc Bazin's resignation; the CIA report labeling Aristide a psychopath and US Senator Jesse Helms's accusations against Aristide; DEA report on drug trafficking in Haiti; and other materials. Also contains letter from US Army General George A. Fisher (Commanding General of the Multinational Forces) to Minister of Justice Jean Joseph Exumé about the Patrick and Eddy Moïse plot (1995).
    - US Treasury Department: Blocked individuals, 1993-1994; 1 folder (Box 125)